Barak Gila

■ barak.gila@gmail.com | 🖀 www.barakgila.com | 🛅 barakgila | 💆 @barakgila

Product- and business-minded software engineer, most experienced on the backend of a product team but comfortable working full-stack. I'm motivated by seeing how my work is impacting users, by talking to them or analyzing data. I also love teaching and mentoring others. I value integrity, transparency, and ownership.

Work Experience _____

Mos, Inc

SOFTWARE ENGINEER April 2020 - March 2021

Mos used software and human advisors to match college students with financial aid. Worked under the CTO as the only full-time engineer.

Languages: Worked full-stack in Typescript and Javascript (Node.js, React/Redux).

Technologies: Serverless architecture on AWS Lambda, and other AWS services DynamoDB and Cloudwatch.

- Introduced industry best practices including postmortems, reusable scripts, and JSON-schema-enforced endpoints to the team.
- · Designed and implemented the messaging system (replacing email/SMS) between agents and users, using Quill.js.
- Implemented "pay later" payment option with payment reminder messages and retries.
- · Built the user-facing aid list, allowing students to add and grants and scholarships and track their progress.
- Integrated the Surveymonkey API to track NPS at various stages in the user journey.

Affirm, Inc San Francisco, California

SENIOR SOFTWARE ENGINEER

Jan 2017 - April 2020

Worked on Affirm's consumer-facing loan product, which let users generate a virtual card in the app to use their loan anywhere. With my team, built the underlying virtual card platform which powered more than 20% of Affirm loans.

Languages: Primarily worked on the Python backend (frameworks including Luigi, Celery, Flask) with some Javascript and React/Redux.

- Designed a new backend service to allow Affirm to approve or deny credit network transactions in real time (99.99% within 3s).
 Created a webapp used by dozens of colleagues, for example to restrict certain cards to a specific merchant.
 The greater control over transactions was critical for Affirm to expand to enterprise merchants and from ecommerce to physical stores.
- Scaled transaction processing logic as loan volume grew by more than 10x by increasing reliability and robustness.
- Conceived and led an initiative to give customers control over their card processing, such as requesting a refund when done with the card.

 This increased loan volume substantially and reduced customer service contacts by as much as 50% for impacted users.
- Developed a take-home interview completed by 1000+ candidates, which better predicted performance and saved interviewing hours.

LEAD, INCLUSION & RETENTION Feb 2018 - Dec 2018

- Led the ten-member Inclusion & Retention group at Affirm within the Diversity & Inclusion program.
- Helped grow our Employee Resource Groups from 5 to 13 groups, and oversaw the budget.

EECS Department, UC Berkeley

Berkeley, California

Undergraduate Student Instructor

Aug 2015 - Dec 2016

- Served as three-time teaching assistant (TA) for CS 170, the upper-division algorithms course of 500 students.
- In fall 2016, served as head TA: I managed course logistics and helped hire TAs and readers.
- · Led discussion sections, designed course materials, and tutored students.

Airbnb San Francisco, California

SOFTWARE ENGINEERING INTERN

May 2016 - Aug 2016

Built support for European bank transactions (SEPA) into the company's new payments service, which handled a fifth of host payouts.

Education _____

University of California, Berkeley

Berkeley, California

B.S. IN ELECTRICAL ENGINEERING AND COMPUTER SCIENCE

Aug 2013 - Dec 2016

- Coursework: Data Structures; Algorithms (undergrad and grad); Artificial Intelligence; Machine Learning
- Scholarships: Regents' Scholarship, Cal Alumni Organization's Leadership Award
- **GPA:** 3.9